this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet
as a radio brings you relevant and
detailed discussions and interviews on
software engineering topics every two
weeks thanks to our audience and the
partners listed on our website for
supporting the program
welcome to software engineering radio
this episode is about Europe lopper
specifically about some of the patterns
of this year's Europe lob conference
this is part of the deal we've made with
hillside Europe when as the radio became
part of a sea of hillside the idea was
to have once a year an episode about
patterns and about interesting things in
the patterns community and what we did
in 2009 was we recall it a couple of
discussions short discussions with
authors pattern authors who had their
papers reviewed at this year's Europe
conference and well this is the episode
that contains the results of that so
well I'm not going to let you know which
people I've talked to you will see and
hear that as you listen to the episode
okay so let's get started the first
topic we want to talk about its product
line engineering reason is that a couple
of people have submitted patterns on
this topic to Europe this year we've had
a workshop where there was a critical
number of product line aware people for
feedback so that was actually quite
useful and the first person I want to
talk about now I want to talk to about
product lines at the patterns she wrote
is Christos running a Hydra stuff hi
Marcos three words about yourself I'm
working for Siemens and I was interested
in aspects for a long time and since I
don't know 2002 I got more and more
interested in product line engineering
since you've left the sinking ship I
wouldn't say it that way it's not a
sinking ship but it's not in it's not
having fair big influence we first
assumed on our business units and
provide engineering definitely yes so
we've had episodes on product line
engineering before so we don't you know
we don't reintroduce the topic but let's
look at the stuff you've written with
your co-author and husband yeah so what
do you write about
so we wanted to more-or-less start off a
bigger collection of patterns on product
line engineering since there is a lot of
stuff out there and good books also but
there are not really many product line
engineering patterns out there resin
attempt from sei but this explains more
or less specific method on product line
engineering the people developed their
with their experience and we thought
that there has to be some way to make
stuff better accessible so we started
off with you know the very early things
like setting up some rolls
how do you do scoping and some general
principles so this is basically meant as
a starting point for other people to
jump in so we've got a lot of feedback
to get more concrete which is it in this
current state of rework of course a
reasonable feedback but it was also you
know you have to start somewhere and
either you start with the nitty gritty
small things or you start more in an
overview way and this is the overview
now and we will continue working on it
and we are glad or happy to accept
everybody else who wants to work with us
yeah this is a good point I mean we
really want to build and I say we
because I want to involved in this want
to build a pedal language for product
line engineering and if you have
experience you would the listener have
experience with this stuff and want to
contribute you're absolutely welcome to
to do that can you give us one or two
examples of some of the parents you've
had in for example that up to the
centralized decision making stuff for
example so when you I need you a product
line then you of course have to support
several products with this and the
classical way of developing products is
that there is somebody from the person
presenting the customer side or the
product portfolio side for each product
a product manager if you do a product
line you do several products together
and you want to build reusable assets
for all those products and if there are
only you know all the product managers
together and they try to come up with
decision which s it should be built
reusable then this eventually might be
quite a fight between those because
everybody wants to you know get the best
out of the product line for his products
I mean they of course are interested in
their own products the overall goal of
product line however is to maximize some
you know if this abstract out like
saving money like increasing time to
mark it like having interoperable
products or things like this and
therefore you need somebody who you know
advocates this common goal and decides
according this current and this guy
needs to also have certain power of
overruling the product so he a good
product manager has to have the benefits
of his product in mind and if you have
good product managers you can't make
them be you know it's good peer team in
deciding together and all the products
so you need a special role to advocate
for the overall product line and
therefore you need a specific role I
mean it's not necessary to have you know
only one person fulfilling their role
for a bigger organization this
definitely will be a group of people
here but you need one person to be
responsible and to decide in the end and
other patterns then revolve around how
do you help this one person to make the
right decisions because this one person
only can decide of course on this you
know it's he still a product manager and
he knows you know the customer side or
the the needs of the different products
and there is another thing you need to
decide what should go into the product
line and this is the the knowledge about
the cost and visit in a very technical
thing so architects typically know about
the cost to estimate what a future cost
right what features cost because you
have first to cast those features into
something like an architecture a
technical decisions so this is the first
step for the architect and then you can
estimate the cost for this and any feeds
expect to the product line product
manager and he according to his
knowledge on the benefits and the
knowledge he got concerning the cost
kinda really decide what's first of all
inside the product line that's the first
decision of the second decisions what is
in
the core asset base so I mean if you as
you say this is quite high level stuff
but I think it reflects your experience
that all the low-level technology stuff
and you know variability implementation
stuff doesn't help much if you can't get
the organization and the people to to
really embrace this idea of product
lines right so if you know how to
implement variability you can do a great
platform the probably never gets used or
cause it does not fulfill the really the
requirement of all the peers you have
and if you do not have to organizational
setup you probably even do the right
platform the problem nobody will use it
cause you don't have to support up the
organization to make people use it so
there are a lot of different facets and
I think there is room for a lot of
patterns or best practices in there so
let's switch roles briefly because I've
also written a paper for Europe loop so
why don't you ask me about that what did
you write tell us so I wrote a paper is
called handling variability and it is
about the more technical stuff so it's
about how you cope with variability in
software systems and of course
especially in product lines that's the
whole thing you want to you want to
express and manage variability in a
consistent and useful way so you have
different levels in there yes that was
very interesting for me when I saw it
can you explain what levels of patterns
you have I mean it's only seven patterns
but nevertheless three there are three
different kinds so I have patterns it's
not at the bottom now because I think
that's better all for the paper starts
at the top so starting from the bottom I
have three patterns that deal with how
which which ways of implementing
variability there are in in artifacts in
all kinds of artifacts these may be
source code files these might be models
or or anything else and maybe I can
introduce one of these patterns later
but the next layer or the next level is
a classification of the expressive power
of how to define a variability or how to
specify a value for a variability so
briefly you can either do selection
which is basically that you say a
variant on or I should say a variation
point can be bound to one of several
alternative configurations you basically
select one of them and the other more
expressive way but also potentially more
complex is that you create manually a
certain configuration for example if you
want to customize the process some kind
of behavioral process in a system you
might simply draw a state machine that
reflects that process drawing this state
machine isn't simply a I select one of
several alternatives but you literally
have to take a language in that case a
state machine in modeling language and
compose the process the state machine
process so that's that's there's two
different things and it's useful to keep
those in mind and the highest level is
about how to distinguish or manage or
separate the low level implementation a
variability and on the other hand side
have a more logical view of the
variability so they have two parents in
here one is basically feature models so
that you take the many many variations
points in the code and group them
together into a logical variation points
that you then basically represent using
a feature model so that means if you
want to select something you just select
in the high-level logical representation
and all the low level implementation
very a variation points kind of are tied
to this high-level point and kind of
automatically change in a consistent way
and the other approach here is to use
basically model of development so you
have a model that expresses the system
in that model you express variations and
then by feeding the variable model into
a generator of course the artifacts that
you get are also variable and since one
model or one part of a model that you
feed into a generator usually results in
different things in the generated code I
mean the example is you have a model
that describes the data structure and
from that you generate you know the
javabean the database structure the XML
for networking so you change the
variability only in the model and then
the generator automatically multiplies
that down it's of course a pure
incidence that you wrote something that
about program engineering that includes
modeling there's
not yes/no it's an incident I don't do
that intentionally but I think that this
whole model driven stuff is a very good
fit for product lines
I also agree completely I mean the more
mature product line is the more you need
support in making an instance of the
product if making a product and I think
that's really the way to go even if you
can't do it probably for the whole life
but for subparts and you should be aware
that supporting instantiation of a
product is one of the main tasks of
building the base assets so if you only
have a number of components there and
nobody knows exactly what to do with
them you you will fail definitely and
and there is also the nice handshake
between our our patterns when it comes
to you know expressing variability not
in code and not in implementation
artifacts but away from code this is
exactly their product management and
development come together in this
variability model in between I think
it's a good middle ground like on the
one hand side you have basically
configuration in future models is very
high level very abstract and if you if
that isn't expressive enough well
without models what you do is you go to
code and and code manually your whatever
specific variant want and the model
driven stuff gives you a middle ground
it's more expressive than selecting from
a feature model it is less expressive
and therefore easier to constrain and
check than code and so if you know that
in some space when some variation point
for example you need a process that can
be described using a state machine well
then give people a state machine
language and not tell them you know
implement the state based behavior in
Java which has no support for state
based behavior right right I mean there
is not only product management but
eventually there are sales and people
who instantiate solution probably at the
customer and it's very easier for them
to understand the domain-specific
language then you know that often cannot
code because there are domain experts
and they are sent to the customer okay I
guess question thank you very much for
for for participating here
thank you so another participant of the
workshop on product lines basically was
did my DD shirts hallo Diddy hi Markus
so um why don't you give us a brief
introduction very brief of who you are
what you do and well that we talk about
your pattern well okay I'm working at
Siemens corporate Technology in Munich
in the Department for software
engineering together with many
colleagues probably from Bush - no and
in Chris - Vanya from the ple
environments of the show five minutes
ago yep perfect so and what's your
pattern about my pattern is about
reverse engineering of variability out
of existing projects so usually you say
don't start a product line engineering
approach and a clean field try to get
the knowledge out of the pass and my
ferritin tries to this tries to describe
how to do that so the assumption is
you're a company you have done product
and certain domain before now you notice
you're doing the same all the time or
similar things and now you want to
product line in fire what you're doing
and you're your parent describes of
about how to extract the variability out
of the existing products right so we
have a lot of knowledge about the
variability on the solution side because
the engineers are smart and they try to
reduce effort as much as possible and on
the other side product line engineering
starts in the problem domain and so we
have to link these two both both two
together and the difficulty is to find
the right features to the variability we
already support so can you give us two
or three bullet points about the most
important steps in doing that how do you
go about extracting existing variability
the most important step in my point is
since it's all about effort whether
where do you get the best results of
what kind of documents and so since we
are looking for features on the user
side it's the user related documents
like user documentation requirement
specifications feature lists if they
exist they are really a good source to
extracted knowledge so it's not
necessarily the existing code base it's
not necessarily the code base if you
have to go to the code base you can do
that
- but you have much more code than
others kinds of documentation usually
and so you have to spend much more
effort to get the right information out
of that right and also its solution site
variability and has nothing to do
necessarily with variations that the
customer want right for every for
example if you do it according to your
change lock in the code you have to look
for every change with it what was the
root cause for that did I do it because
I needed another kind of functionality
there and justify if there's a feature
behind it or if it's simply a bug fix
so in some sense your paper describes
the the ugly truth because you don't
start with a nice very systematic domain
analysis but you rather say okay let's
let's let's look at what we have and
extract it from there
yeah the domain analysis this is
something kind of theoretical in the
beginning it's difficult to do it
completely and there's a lot of
knowledge in the past and this is
probably much better than the forecast
on the future right ok very good
thanks didi thanks Marcus so the next
person we want to talk to is close mark
vault
who wrote about well we won't say that
so close hello hello Marcus so please
say who you are yeah I'm Klaus Marquardt
I work for dragon medical billing
life-supporting systems and my position
is platform program manager okay so you
could have talked about the product line
stuff that we've talked about before but
we wanted you to talk to something else
you've written parents about dealing
with complexity this year so I think
that's a very relevant topic it's also
one that's not so very easy to grasp so
before we look at your patterns
what is complexity let's let's look at
complexity just a bit from the outside
because I think complexity is a as a
friend or a comrade to our project we
happen to have complex projects and I
wonder why that is this is maybe a
natural thing to happen because the more
simple projects
are more easily done so they are less
disgusting and less attractive to
engineers because engineers love
complexity and they love solving complex
problems if they are solvable we don't
want to give up yeah right absolutely
and there's a large subjective part to
complexity like some people are more
capable and grasping and dealing with
complexity than others on the other hand
complexities of project risk so we need
to deal with complexity we we needn't
just kind of embrace it but we also need
to tackle it to some extent but with
this we need to be somewhat careful
because what I learned is that if you
just start fighting complexity yeah like
introducing more control more measures
more tracking whatever more abstraction
abstraction layers it's somehow it it
strikes back at a different place so if
you add more management level effort for
example I kind of increased the
complexity and maybe you even set the
wrong triggers it's a little bit like
with energy right you can't create or
destroy energy you can only change the
form so if you if you if you put in more
management to reduce some of the
complexity you create new communication
overhead and that's also complexity
right absolutely so complexity is also
related to the size of the project so
when you have a certain size you can't
really tell where but when you are in a
complex situation you identify that
suddenly the complexity is way higher
than it was before just by adding maybe
too much approach it so so the approach
you have or you proposal you've written
about in your pattern language is to
let's say tackle complexity indirectly
by by doing what the the usual approach
like dividing conquer or separation of
concern it doesn't really help with
really really really complex systems
it's more like slicing a problem slicing
a problem can make for smaller problems
right but when you have
many different influencing factors then
you cannot resolve all of them by just
saying separations of concern and this
is why the the approach I propose is
that you deal with your contributing
factors so you have many potential
factors contributing to your complexity
like including size including amount of
requirements including how many teams
are involved including continents
including what kind of process you have
to follow and so on a positive cycle
density of then of course there's also
technical diversity in there and so on
so yes there's a lot of contributing
factors and my approach is to write them
down and classify them whereas I'm not
the first one who's addressed
classifying complexity Brooks had
started this already and he's famous for
his essential versus accidental
complexity and this is helpful already I
propose to add another dimension to it
so it's kind of orthogonal let us say we
have not only essential and accidental
complexity but we have also imposed and
chosen complexity and there I consider
real web projects I've seen where we say
ok this kind of component is being out
sourced or developed with a different
tool or whatever developed by different
team at another continent and so the the
outline of the project so how its
defined kind of imposes some complexity
at least often it does and and what do
you do about it
first thing is I need to become aware of
that now so this is this is where I say
just write down all your contributing
factors the typical thing is you are not
aware of all contributing factors in the
very beginning of the project so this is
an ongoing process just just like risk
management I was about to mention second
thing is when you identify that you have
complexity issues and many factors that
you consider being imposed then you need
to take control of them
and this is this is the most important
thing so things that are imposed from
the outside are basically out of your
control
yeah but most organizations it's
ultimately more important to have a
successful project then a failed project
that has adhere to all official
boundaries so we don't have time to step
through all your patterns but can you
give us two or three examples of how you
get from imposed to chosen in order to
make the the complexity is controllable
yeah sure I can maybe the the one that
is obvious in what we've talked about
this is the renegotiation so when we
identify certain imposed factors as
obstacles to protic success then it's
the duty of the protein managers to make
this clear and to approach their
stakeholders or our sponsors and say in
this setting it can't possibly work and
when this is being accepted then such a
factor suddenly goes down from imposed
to chosen because the project may then
choose whether this is effective to
consider or not so they may choose to do
something else and this is what what I
mean and taking control or gaining
control over your complexity
contributing factors then there are some
some more or less I'd say obvious things
like peacemaker growth that you do not
try to solve all problems at once so
this is kind of slicing down complexity
because you you do not look to all
problems you have to solve but you only
look for a small set of problems
so do you piecemeal growth you mean
growing your project and team size in a
piecemeal way or the system you're
building basically it's the system
you're building yeah but teams agile
idea it's it's basically the edge
already Ania
whereas I I must say the edge lists
haven't been the first mentioned this
but today it's known by at a write more
what I find useful is to budget the
complexity that comes from the
combinatorial explosion you have to tell
you have to explain that okay if you
have many things that you can configure
yeah I see are many options to support
or whatever then you gain complexity
because you have to support each branch
each combination juices and so on and
you have not only to implement it but
also to understand it to document it to
put in the requirements to test it and
so on and typically due to
indecisiveness or due to light
requirements changes you tend to add to
that computer ability and that this is a
bad thing so if you have a budget like I
only support this amount of decisions
that are visible to end users and
administrators yeah and then whenever
you you are being approached by saying
how we need to do this and that but in a
configurable way then you say okay which
other configurations which may I take
away of course the challenge of all of
that is that you need let's say
political clout to be able to do that as
a project manager you have to stand up
to the stakeholders I know we won't do
these other five different configuration
factors which is because it's gonna kill
us and they probably won't believe and
say yeah yeah yeah do it anyway I think
that's the problem in some sense whether
the project manager is kind of left
alone in that respect because the
typical situation is that stakeholders
say we want this in angels and you say
yes that's easily done but even if they
say it's tough nobody cares because
stakeholders typically don't talk to
engineers but also the project manager
yeah but the project managers is
responsible for for scoping the protein
in a way that it can be successful yes
another one is that I consider important
and it's it's not mentioned in the the
AJ world is that project teams need to
gather domain knowledge right of course
that's that's kind of a myth that just
software engineering skills can solve
all complexity problems yes so well what
you're saying is that if you understand
the domain something that
apparently complex maybe isn't because
you know understand why and what's going
on the the personal ability to deal with
complexity it's certainly increased if
you understand the domain you're working
for yeah yeah okay very good
that was brief but I think that's it we
have to cover five other people for this
episode so close thanks very much for
being on the show oh you're welcome
so the next set of patterns we're going
to talk about is about open source
projects about successful opens open
source projects and sometimes I got the
performance of open source projects and
we were talking to Michael Weiss hi hi
so um why don't you briefly say who you
are what you do for a living
I'm Michael Weiss I'm from Germany from
University originally currently living
in Ottawa Canada called University
I'm also this use conference chair for
for Europe up I think that's one of the
rare case where the conference chair had
time to actually write something for the
conference is chairing so what is your
parent stuff about it's I was I'm very
interested in open source projects
happen in moved in a number of them in
through a variety of ways both as a
developer as well instead of working
with some open source project so I
thought of for a while to capture some
of that knowledge and patterns form
hopefully something larger at the end
yeah so like a big pattern language kind
of thing right yes and the patterns you
have now is that already the complete
language or is it more consider like a
starting point it's a starting point
already so why don't you give us two or
three examples or well no let's let's
start with the general problem I mean
open source projects probably aren't all
the same so your idea was to classify
them and find out what the best
practices are right yes or whatever the
title here performance of open source
project so I was trying to focus on in a
specific aspect because there's so many
aspects you could talk about the
community you could talk about your IP
and I don't know what to stop I
I was looking at particularly here how a
small to medium-sized company could
develop the products faster using an
open-source approach so not necessarily
by using open-source that's one
component but also using open sources a
strategy right okay um and when I say
performance it's about you know that
that open source really helps you reduce
the time it takes to develop sorry yeah
that you want to increase the quality of
the software for a variety of reasons
for example you build another pieces of
software that have already been proven
right so it's not about performance in
the sense that a system is fast ility so
this is the performance the Waveland we
talk about product development yeah okay
so okay now two or three patterns that
are representative of what you've worked
on I see penguins here and one that's a
paralyze particularly fond of and it's I
think it's one that you can really say
that is clearly a pattern in that and in
that area that has been identified you
know in there its nature by others so
this is called credible promise and the
reason why is about the hangman's it's
well not just because of course the
alliteration tutor to open-source
writing right then X being yeah but
actually be more deeply because one key
thing that you have to dress in
open-source as you want to get other
developers to contribute to your project
so many people need to start out think
about open source and say well let's
make my code open source and the
developers will come well it doesn't
quite happen like that you know the
metaphor the the the the the Penguins
here helps is with an even penguins when
they're on the flow of ice you see them
on flows of flows of ice and they you
know they're all hungry but none of them
dives in first
you know what the others diving at at
the same time yep so this basically
creates a critical mass of the bulk you
know plenty due to open source and now
the right the path is about that you
have to have a critical mass
what are you call incredible promise
okay so right so the that's the concept
here is that
what I'm what I'm starting an
open-source project it has to be enough
it has to be implemented for enough OS
will want to contribute right okay not
too far because then it's wrong
interesting for them
right but it shouldn't just be an idea
right okay mmm very rarely an idea were
working with the cases like send bailiff
or a couple of others you know the the
is BN s BN system for example there were
there was just some very developers with
a lot of reputation who threw out an
idea and people joined usually you have
to show something Albert III would have
it just saw the title and I would have
expected it's written from the
perspective of the adoption users
because you're Lee you only use open
source projects if you believe that they
are able to deliver on a promise image
this may be another facet habit this is
from the person I want to yeah sure
created opens don't approach it around
opens all right perhaps I have some code
or starting from scratch or scratch or
what others to join mmm-hmm another one
another one did I I think building a
shoulder on the shoulders of others is
wondering that I found to be very true
and one poacher that we I was quite
closely involved in the first prototype
of the system was a web conferencing
system we put it together in in a very
short time using open-source components
you know we need to convert PDF
PowerPoint to PDF so we used OpenOffice
and variety building blocks that you
could very quickly prove the
functionality that you wanted to build
and then you could you know maybe decide
well maybe there's a better way of doing
something or you can strip down allows
you to get up to speed problem he
basically addresses you know how do you
really build that critical mass that you
need quickly and one key way is you know
used assets or components code that I've
written here are green red always yours
exactly only that the steering wheel
that's important maybe uh something that
differentiates was a lot from yeah
yeah one last one maybe sure parallel
developments can acute because of the
picture so yeah it shows you two two two
two planes yeah in parallel so basically
the need here is this or do you know so
do you always you have users who depend
on all developers who depend on the
software that you're writing so at the
same time you want to evolve it here you
know there's a tension here obviously
yeah and so the the basically the
tension can be resolved by creating one
release dream that stable and another
release dream that we or multiple where
you have the audio or you can maintain
all these experimental developments it's
not specific to open source absolutely
not no yes but it's you know it's very
visible in open source right you have
many projects it goes your many protein
that have you know
releases this is the zip file that you
load right and this is the nightly build
and this is the kind of the the most
curable right so they can really
different neural risk levels that people
are tempering so you're obviously
planning to continue to work on this
life I think that could be an
interesting topic for for a for full
show so I think once it's enough stuff I
think so you can talk about it for 45
minutes I guess we can get back together
and do a photo thanks for being here
thank you so here is our next guest on
this show of short interviews and our
next guest is Lisa vadym hi hi so well
welcome to the show thank you and please
give you our listeners a chance to get
to know you a little bit okay so I'm 47
years old I live in the US
although I am Norwegian okay I started
my career from computer science working
for marine seismic where I did the
software development and I did that for
some years and after that I've been in
software management okay and the stuff
you've written about at this you
and also in previous years I understand
is distributed teams right yes and your
patterns help cope with the challenges
and problems and yeah well issues in
distributed team software development
yes
so we over time we realized we do a lot
of that in the company but the
challenges have increased as we are
growing more and more global and
including more and more geographic
geographical sites in what we're doing
so what's the the biggest three
challenges and in this setting and and
how do some of your patterns address
those challenges so I would say most of
the challenges if you go back and find
the root cause you'll find that you end
up on communication a very big challenge
is how do you communicate on
architecture and a very heavy technical
material so if you are multiple sites
it's difficult enough when you are
together but you are you spread out and
maybe the software industry doesn't have
very very clear ways of communicating
architecture and no very very clear
standards how do we really make sure
that everybody are on the same page
understand the architecture and the
development that is done locally at the
site is compliant
or-or-or is following the architectural
principles and it's breaking it so and
what do you suggest to do about that so
I think most of the planners so the
planners are actually kind of in three
levels there are some that are for the
team and they would be more applicable
in within this area there is also things
about how you set up the whole project
and how the organization around can
support the project so again it's around
communication and you know the ability
actually to come together so that's a
fundamental recommendation I would make
I know in the industry today it's very
often difficult for teams to be allowed
to travel and come together but if you
really are doing complex development
over some time not just a few weeks but
maybe a years type of development the
investment in actually bringing people
together is very important so basically
what we suggest that first of all you
come together early and me
and build up the knowledge of each other
in the team and build up the trust and
start developing the architecture
together and then you come together on
certain intervals
you know maybe every six week I think
that's what we would recommend not more
than six weeks and you can you know
travel to multiple sites so it doesn't
need to be the same people traveling all
the time so if you have two or three
locations you you alternate so that
everybody you spend some time traveling
during the times that that you meet
together there's another thing that's
kind of the foundation here is some
agile thinking what if you work with
iterations try to finish an iteration
together and start the next right and
then you try to align on the
architecture on the user experience and
and sort of you know you kind of align
everybody on where you are what the user
feedback is plan for the next iteration
then you may have a couple of iterations
that you are done that are done remotely
but again the next time you meet you
synchronize it with an iteration
transition phase so this whole travel
business can become quite expensive so I
guess the primary reason for having
distributed teams is probably not the
idea that you want to save money but
more that you can't motivate or make you
know the good people you have everywhere
to move together so this is not about
outsourcing right no it's definitely not
about outsourcing although I think
people who do outsourcing may find
interesting material in there but they
will they will argue that if they do
outsourcing and then have led all this
travel cost and the benefit goes away so
that's why they don't travel which of
course is where outsourcing event yes so
if we park that for a couple of minutes
we can talk about you know where we came
from doing this so like many big
organizations they grow by acquisitions
or there may be a desire to be present
in a certain market which means that you
want to start up an activity in another
country in another
geographical area and over time you will
realize you have experts in multiple
locations that when you go for something
new they need to be involved
and it's not really feasible to move the
motor on-site yeah so that's kind of the
background I think for a lot of what's
happening when you're outsourcing I
think there are other patterns not
necessarily just from this but also from
other organizational patterns that you
need to think about how you structure
the work versus where people are and
even if you're outsourcing if the whole
team is in its one location actually and
you've outsourced the whole project they
are actually together yes yeah yeah so
two or three more representative
patterns I guess the idea that you
should travel and meet is well it's in
some sense it's obvious it's just that
many people probably don't want to see
the reality yeah but it's that combined
with what you are actually doing when
you are together so maybe we should talk
a little bit about what happens when
you're not together yes exactly so we
have some patterns about you know
flexible work hours for instance so
that's very important when you are in
very different time zones so that's what
we started doing initially it was a lot
between Europe and the US and it wasn't
such a big challenge as if we when
included Asia and you have teams in the
US and teams in Asia that don't really
have any overlap in the earth time it
becomes very challenging so trying to
emulate some of the meetings and
communication that you have in agile
teams by a combination of more
formalized working meeting time so that
you know when people are people are
available so you can okay if I have an
issue I know that you know this evening
there will be a get-together and I can
bring it up yeah with a development
environment and communication tools for
the team so that they can also hook up
whenever they need to chat video webcams
yeah okay do you also look at the
tooling like you know distributed
version management or something like yes
I would like to talk about that too so
that's another thing that is very
important and I know when I'm presenting
this in in at conferences and talking to
people from other companies they ask a
lot of questions around that and say
this is very a very difficult team so
that's where
some of the practices for on a company
level or at least for the engineering
organization come in that you have to do
an investment in trying to standardize
workflows and tools so that we actually
use the same every word we do actually
have an internal source control and
build configuration management system
that is totally transparent on locations
right which is very I think I don't I'm
not sure we recognize the importance of
it but without that tool I think we
would have been in trouble if you have
different source control different code
bases it makes it very very difficult I
think that's it's also important because
although you said that you cannot
obviously move everybody to the same
place I think you will have many people
moving around over the years like I mean
if you have the chance to go to
basically any country on the world some
people will want to do that and if you
have the same infrastructure everywhere
it's much easier for them to get up to
speed again yes I'm actually often
asking other companies how they're doing
this when they are large organizations
and I realized that we may be a little
bit special in this that we are
operating as one company worldwide and
so we have when you're moving around
from location to location you will see
that you meet the same tools and the
same maybe even the same to some extent
the same culture the same thinking and I
think that happens also because we do
move a lot of people right so typically
in each of our development locations
maybe up to 40% of the people there will
be what we call experts they are not
local yeah and they move regularly
around in the system and bring knowledge
from one location to another location
is that a side effect or do you think
that's even an S&S necessity to make
this distributed environment work I
think in our organization is deliberate
I know I think it's maybe not 40 percent
is necessary but some movement of people
also to build up that trust and respect
thing because to avoid this them and
they enough right type of thinking yeah
okay anything else I forgot well I your
pattern stuff is probably much bigger
one more you want to think it's kind of
a highlight yes so let's talk a little
bit about what's happening also on the
big picture in the organization so there
are things that need to be in place for
this to work also on the organizational
side initially when we started we tended
to not understanding clear so you might
have people in one location reporting to
a local manager but actually working for
a project that was based in another
location so that was difficult so so you
need to set it up as a clear
organization around the project with
clear decision-making so it's not
confusing who is doing what and and also
maybe things like financial system and
human resource systems to be able to to
work with that one project team which is
actually on multiple locations okay very
nice
thank you thank you so here is our next
guest it's Paris of Carillo I hope
that's the spelled correctly it's pretty
much okay hi so so please introduce
yourself so people know who you are
so I'm from academia I'm a professor of
software engineering at the University
of Groningen in the Netherlands and I've
been doing research in the field of
patterns for the past maybe six or seven
years and I've started together with a
couple of colleagues here in Europe lob
over student Anil Harrison an attempt to
try and reflect upon the actual usage of
patterns so not just about writing new
patterns but about using the existing
ones mm-hmm kind of case studies and
scenarios where they fulfill their
promises exactly so we are looking at
both practitioners and academics what
kind of approach is existing in the
industry right now approaches that are
not particularly scientifically sound
but they still work approaches that can
you know use patterns to solve different
problems in companies or organizations
yeah
and on the other hand we have academics
that are performing research about the
use of patterns try to make it more
systematic if you like so this year you
have submitted a paper about using
patterns to avoid the architectural
knowledge in a system just disappearing
into nowhere once the system is built a
problem we all know right so why don't
you elaborate on the problem for a
minute or two and then we look at a
couple of patterns or well how you used
parents to to avoid rice problem so
software engineering is in essence
knowledge intensive activity throughout
the whole lifecycle the the different
roles in software engineering produce
knowledge and consume knowledge and by
knowledge we mean pretty much every
every information that is relevant for
example the stakeholders may have
concerns about the system to be built if
you like requirements this is important
knowledge the architects make decisions
about the system this is also knowledge
those decisions have rationale why where
they make this is also important
knowledge the problem is that usually
this knowledge resides in people's heads
its tacit knowledge and eventually
people move around organizations and the
knowledge dissipate it gets lost so we
are trying to solve this problem because
when knowledge get lost people spend an
awful lot of effort and of course money
to try to recover there so the the other
side of this problem is that documenting
knowledge is very expensive if you have
people like architects who are very
expensive themselves you cannot really
ask them can you stop what you're doing
and write down all the design decisions
you made that's not gonna happen in
practice yeah so suggestions to solve
that problem so we are trying to solve
this problem by using patterns well that
was not a surprise
so far so good right the thing about
patterns is that they can provide you
with a cheap way to document the
knowledge and how'd they do that
patterns carry a lot of important
baggage with them so they have a very
well-documented problem they have a very
elaborate solution as well as
consequences related patterns and all
that information now this is reusable
knowledge so patterns are applied in a
system and architects and designers
apply those patterns even if architects
and designers do not explicitly document
their decisions they have applied those
patterns so just by looking at those
matters you can somehow mind the
decisions that were made so you're
trying to extract which patterns have
been used in a system from existing
resources code documentation whatever
exactly and because a pattern has a
well-defined set of circumstances where
it should be used and we know why it's
used what it does that allows you to
kind of infer that those problems the
parent solves are there in the system
exactly so we have created a kind of a
meta model what does it mean to have an
architectural or design decision what
are the different you know requirements
associated with that what are the
different artifacts like models or code
that are derived in that and we sort of
use the information from the patterns to
fill in all the knowledge that has been
lost so we are inferring for example
what we call context knowledge so the
problem part of the pattern which is
somehow related to the requirements you
know you applied I don't know pipes and
filters just because you wanted to have
a system that implements a specific
process which is sequential then we have
the reasoning knowledge which is
basically why you made what the kind of
decision you made and why and then we
have the design knowledge which is the
actual
and result the the solution that came
with a pattern in terms of components
and connectors and of course essentially
code now since you're in academia you
cannot just you know walk around through
the world and say this is great I can do
this is I can just say my experience
tells me this is cool stuff so as some
people believe it others don't but you
can't do this you have to prove this
stuff so do you have any evidence did
you do any experiments that kind of
proved that this approach of a you know
recovering architecture through patterns
works not so far okay what we have as
experience so far didn't have to do with
patterns it had to do with how
organizations what kind of knowledge
they they use in their business and how
that knowledge helps them to perform
their day-to-day activities we found out
a bunch of problems there but we also
found out a number of solutions for
example we saw that in different
organizations document acknowledges you
are expensive so another solution is to
have personalization which means that
you don't necessarily write everything
down but you know what personal what
okay yes so this is also you know a more
pragmatic way to to spread knowledge
within the organization as far as this
particular work about patterns we are
just starting with this and our aim is
to basically implement this thing into a
repository that acts as a tool to
recover knowledge in specific case
studies and we are of course looking for
industrial partners we have a couple of
companies in mind but no specific
results yet okay and you've also run a
workshop here where you've tried to
trick people into using this stuff so
you can verify that it actually works
that's exactly right
we made a sort of an empirical study
where we had a control group and a test
group and the control group had to
document knowledge of an existing system
out explicitly using patterns and the
test group did the opposite they were
asked to explicitly use patterns so we
sort of gathered the data out of this
experiment and we still are analyzing
the data but as a preliminary result we
found out that the quality of the
knowledge that has been recovered with
the use of patterns is higher than
without in some sense that's one of the
original promises that parents you know
set out to deliver which is if everybody
knows patterns and if you mentioned them
in conversations and also in
documentation and other things this acts
as a likely a little bit of like like a
macro right you mentioned the word you
can expand it to all this knowledge
that's behind the pattern exactly your
kind of trying to prove that and we're
trying to fill in the details so just by
saying that you know this is a client
server using a broker
you've mentioned two patterns but you
haven't said anything about the details
what was the problem you were trying to
solve what other alternative patterns
yet we have considered why you chose a
specific one and what are the
consequences to the system quality
attributes for example so all this
information is implicit when you say the
name of the pattern and we're trying to
have a more systematic approach of
documenting that so cool very nice
so I guess once you've finished this
work you might maybe come back to show
and tell the listeners what what the
results are
we'll be happy to do that and well in
our community we usually make a lot of
claims I mean the academic community we
make a lot of claims but not always
provide evidence and our approach is
evidence-based so we're really
performing empirical research and trying
to have concrete evidence that this
stuff actually works it would be a good
and new buzzword evidence-based software
engineering you know there is
evidence-based medicine so something
like that well that's what empirical
software engineering innocence okay okay
thanks for being on the show thank you
so much okay so here is yet another
guest for this episode on Europe plot
pattern material and pattern people
welcome Thanks and I didn't mention your
name because I wasn't quite
how to pronounce correctly so far to
introduce yourself and pronounce your
name correctly I'm Michael Aranda from
Tampere University of Technology which
is of course located at Finland okay
which we've had an episode with Yuna
Pekka tolven and from metal case so
people probably know the the accent so
so you've written a paper on
architecture patterns for distributed
embedded control systems and before we
look at some of the patterns I think
it's a good idea to to let our listeners
know what distributed control systems
are and what the problem is why there is
specific architectural patterns for them
maybe I should tell a little about our
project we are doing architectural
evaluation for the immediate control
systems industry in Finland and we have
visited some company stir and quality
depart language there the systems are
like elevators or forest harvester or
mining trucks and so on you get the idea
which kind of machine we are talking
about and the main characteristics of
software in the industry are there has
to be reliable of course for tolerant
they have real-time requirements and the
well maintainability is one one big
question because a long lifetime yeah
yeah yeah let's look at two or three of
the patterns and we will probably can't
cover the whole paper but that's
unnecessary so let's look at two or
three of the patterns that are maybe
non-obvious to some of our listeners
maybe well maybe I should start with one
that is quite fundamental it's called
separate real time and usually with
these machines you have real time
requirements but of course you want some
higher level functionality there you
want to provide a logging error handling
capability maybe debugging that and user
interface for the operator so you need
high-end PC there and but the problem is
that usually these high-end services are
more volatile they are not for tolerant
so much and there is no no way that we
can take the risk that the real time
part of the system can be
we interfere with this program so so you
have to separate these two to NGO but
not nothing danger is going to happen
more example in the forest harvester you
have to make sure that the log is not
fit through the capping that's actually
checked yeah okay so and so the thing
knows the length of the log so you know
when it knows the speed and the distance
to the cabin in calculator and the
direction of the feeding women harvester
head is feeling the log so and so what
you're saying is basically as you see
you should separate those two but if the
if the real-time part has to feed
information to let's say user interface
and that is slow yeah how do you avoid
that the slow user interface you know
slows down the real-time part there
needs to be some interaction or
something in there well you have a bus
there and you have a message queue that
is used at between there actually that's
a pattern in our language okay and so
it's sold and in addition to these two
levels there can be more of course their
exact mean third level that is emergency
stop right there you have very very very
strict response time requirements and
also you have to make sure it really
stops when it's supposed so so we had
once an episode where we talked to close
market who is working in these life
support systems and what I think is
funny is that in their case the
emergency well it's not an emergency
stop it's an emergency
open the oxygen line so the guy doesn't
die and that's actually mechanical there
is no software in it at all
well basically the MS is top level is
something that is really in the hardware
there might be some software in there
okay and of course maybe the software
bodies just like it is it is over
everything else is overridden in the
software it's the priority one stop
everything another one well here's some
parameter authority
pairen well as we are talking about
distributed systems here we have
multiple nodes that are located in
different places in the machine
the decision-making is a challenge how
you do make decision and ensure that the
consequences will be safe we will not
harm the machine or the operator know
the solution basically is to add one
dedicated component that has the system
state
it keeps the state in one place and make
sure that the information is new enough
there and every other node in the system
they will have to ask permission to
perform an action from this super wasn't
note problem of course can be that there
will be or there might be a bottleneck
or performance performance earth sorry
communication problem lack there if
everybody asks the guy in the central
decision-maker for everything of course
for example a machine stop as we
discussed already you can't ask that you
do it you go to the safe mode
yeah that's ask anything but usually
when you start something for example a
driver could ask from the authority note
that can I start engine and maybe
there's some some thing for example
handbrake is on so it no well maybe
transmission controller would ask if
there is a hydraulic or something like
that and maybe third one it's called
sandbox and the idea is that usually in
these systems you have also third by
applications such as remote diagnostics
or or maybe in case of mining trucks
they have their own software at mine
that is sending drilling plans to the
machine or or information you should go
there and pick up some stuff yeah
and it's a problem because we need to
offer interface for third party to how
they can use the system but they have to
do it in a way that is safe it cannot
interfere with the normal operation of
the system of course so we basically say
that you should add a sandbox or well
kind of virtual mess in there where you
put the software and you can give the
interface
is to the third-party developer
something if it agrees is the time to
market of this software for the
third-party benefits them and of course
when it's sandbox it it doesn't mmm
cause any harm to the actual operating
software of the machine mm-hmm so since
you're talking about harvesters and a
mining truck do you actually get to play
with all these machines when you do this
research or is this important we know
okay but we have tried the simulator
it's nice cool okay so I guess um well I
guess that's it well pretty much I would
say that wanting more we are continuing
this work now we have 35 patterns oh
yeah and we are developing a language
and our goal is to get a generative
language for this domain
new developers can take it and okay this
is this is the way I'm going to build
this machine but if submitted only like
six or six or seven pattern yeah we we
have a part of those now written down
here and we want to get feedback on them
before we go forward and write all of
them we have all these like I'm pattern
ideas yes yes and there are some notes
on there so this is work in progress so
once you finish this stuff why don't you
get back to me and we will do an episode
on this in detail because I we've had a
couple of things on embedded systems but
not enough and well the nice thing about
pattern language is for me as an
interviewer it's very easy to step
through and ask the right questions
because I just take the pattern title
and formulate it as a question so if
you're interested just get back to me
when you're finished so cool
thanks for being here thanks
thanks for listening to software
engineering radio software engineering
radio is an educational program brought
to you by hillside Europe if you want
more information about the podcast and
all the other episodes visit our website
at SE - radio dot net if you want to
support us you can donate to the SU
radio team via the website or you can
advertise for se radio for example by
clicking on the Digg reddit delicious
links and the slash dot button to
contact the team please send email to
team at s e - radio net or if you
specific to an episode please use the
comments facility on the website so
other people can react to your comments
this episode of se radio as well as all
other episodes are licensed under the
creative comments 2.5 license please see
the website for details thanks to
Charlie Crowell and the pot site Music
Network for the music used in this show
the song is called Vegas Achtung